<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>banski</title><link href="http://banski.github.io/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://banski.github.io/feeds/experiments.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://banski.github.io/</id><updated>2015-07-15T00:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>NA as tag re-visited</title><link href="http://banski.github.io/na-as-tag-re-visited.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-07-15T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>selpa'i</name></author><id>tag:banski.github.io,2015-07-15:na-as-tag-re-visited.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Quite a while ago (3 years!?) I wrote an article about NA acting as a tag and even though I had discarded the idea back then it reappeared recently, both in ctefaho's attempts at formalizing Lojban's tags and in gleki's altatufa parser. Now seems as good a time as any to add my own ideas to the mix before they won't get heard anymore.
The old idea was that the argument tagged by {na} would be the thing that negates or contradicts the bridi, the thing due to which the bridi is false. This seems to be the idea that ctefaho has recently picked up for {na} as tag.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A little while ago, unrelated to any tag-ness, I proposed that the {ku} of {NA ku} be elidible, allowing such phrases as {na ro da zvati} &amp;quot;Not everyone is there&amp;quot; (where the {ku} immediately gets auto-inserted because {na} can't tag anything, but it saves a syllable, and adds more colloquial options for bridi-final {na}.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My new idea (which is inspired by Toaq Dzu, but since I don't know how long it will be before I can publish version 1.0 I am just going to talk about it here) keeps {na ro da zvati} grammatical and preserves its meaning, but no longer inserts a {ku} - because {na} becomes a sort of tag. If the meaning is preserved, then {na} cannot be a variation of {fi'o se natfe} or {xoi se natfe}, as that would make {ro da} an argument of {na} and remove it from the x1 place of {zvati}, which is not what's happening here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what's happening? The idea is that {na} becomes a &amp;quot;prefix&amp;quot; that simply marks the following sumti as being such that the bridi is false with it in that place. Thus, it does not change a bridi's truth value to move {na} from the selbri in front of a sumti (as long as scope is respected).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;dl class="docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Why is this useful? Two reasons.&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;ol class="first last arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;{ku} becomes elidible after {na}, giving the speaker more freedom (e.g. for slang or for poetry - just more room to play), and saving a syllable quite often compared to {na ku}.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The second reason - and this is straight from Toaq Dzu - is that it ... allows the removal of the NA JA leftwards negation construction from the grammar (wooosh!). The point of NA JA is to negate the left side of a connective, but it is not a very pretty part of the grammar (who hasn't gotten thrown off by {ja'a .e} at least once?). E.g. {mi na je do} means &amp;quot;not me but you&amp;quot; (but the &amp;quot;not&amp;quot; comes around rather gardenpathy). With NA being able to &amp;quot;tag&amp;quot; sumti, the equivalent {na mi je do} &amp;quot;[not me] and [you]&amp;quot; would become possible. (This has the additional benefit of enabling {NA JA NA} (connecting two NA with JA), which is currently impossible because of {NA JA}.)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course one does not need to remove {NA JA} from the grammar to enjoy the benefits of {NA SUMTI}. It is already useful enough on its own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(Note: This is all hypothetical, and does not constitute a formal proposal.)&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><category term="na"></category><category term="bai"></category></entry></feed>